<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The example of euyll tongues</title>
            <title>Of euyll tongues.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1525</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110674</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846174</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846174</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00474)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 20:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The example of euyll tongues</title>
                  <title>Of euyll tongues.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1525?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>An edition of: Of euyll tongues (STC 24115.5).</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Libel and slander --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:11124:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut depicting the punishment of two people (one in the stocks and one tied to a tree) enduring punishment</figDesc>
                  <head>¶The example of euyll tongues.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11124:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>WIth pyte moued to my payne I dyde me dres</l>
               <l>To ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people what doth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt greua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</l>
               <l>I ſaye yll tonges full of bytter crewelnes</l>
               <l>In this worlde may be no greter penaunce</l>
               <l>Thes be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clappers of ſorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkorges of vengans</l>
               <l>Theſe preuy morderers theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berous hell wedes</l>
               <l>Becauſe of grete meſchefe &amp; dyſtroyers of good dedys</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yf there were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde none other punyſhement</l>
               <l>But yll tonges onely in eſpecyall</l>
               <l>Of very ryght it were ſuffycyent</l>
               <l>Seyenge how euery creature nowe ouer all</l>
               <l>Is ſodeynly ſmyten w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this venemous ſpere mortall</l>
               <l>Of comberous tonges that god ne man dredys</l>
               <l>Bycauſe of myſchefe &amp; dyſtroyers of good dedys</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bothe ryche and poore be brought in torment</l>
               <l>By this curſed ſlo worme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwelleth worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a tode</l>
               <l>I mene the yll tonge that venymous ſerpent</l>
               <l>Whiche many good doer deſtroyed with a worde</l>
               <l>Who ledeth theyr lyfe now in peaſyble concorde</l>
               <l>Full fewe for yll tonges ſo moche ſorowe bredys</l>
               <l>They be cauſe of myſchefe &amp; dyſtroyed good dedys</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No enemy ſo lytell we out hym to doute</l>
               <l>Ne none ſo grete rome but remedy may be founde</l>
               <l>If it in tyme be perceyued and brought oute</l>
               <l>Than to a good ende it may rebounde</l>
               <l>But an yll tonge ſo brode renrieth the ſounde</l>
               <l>Fro bad to worſe and ſo myſchefe ſpedys</l>
               <l>Whiche cauſed many a man to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>drawe good dedys</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11124:2"/>
               <l>The tonge is inſtrument of lyes treaſon &amp; trechery</l>
               <l>And cauſeth warre morther myſchefe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ende</l>
               <l>Grete multytude of other with ypocryſy</l>
               <l>Rebellyons thefte dyſcorde full yll to defende</l>
               <l>Fyghtynge chydynge to ſtryfe euer Intende</l>
               <l>With ſhame &amp; ſclaunder to yll fortune all ledes</l>
               <l>Lo how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge cauſed myſchefe &amp; dyſtroyed good dedes</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some theues eſcapen &amp; many true men be hanged</l>
               <l>It is dayly ſene in this worlde rounde</l>
               <l>Faythfull people by yll tonges be condempned</l>
               <l>That to vntruth there dydes neuer dyde founde</l>
               <l>But he that cometh in daunger of an yll tonge</l>
               <l>Seldome or neuer he ſcapeth there fro</l>
               <l>For by an yll tonge the good name is ſoone a go</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And this yll Ioynt of mooſt dyſpyte</l>
               <l>Sormounteth all venyme of ſerpentes fell</l>
               <l>They haue ſuche malycyous appetyte</l>
               <l>They may be lykened to the fende of hell</l>
               <l>The ſorowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by them is rered no man may tell</l>
               <l>The true ſeruaunt put out of fauour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is pyte &amp; wo</l>
               <l>For by an euyll tonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good name is ſoone a go</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A falſe tonge wyll euer Imagyne and ſaye</l>
               <l>That neuer by creature was ſayd ne thought</l>
               <l>And this hath be ſene and is euery daye</l>
               <l>The fader and mother betraye &amp; in ſorowe brought</l>
               <l>Many good folke hath ſclaunder dere bought</l>
               <l>As loſte theyr goodes and theyr lyues alſo</l>
               <l>For by an yll tonge the good name is ſoone a go</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11124:3"/>
               <l>Many there be that neuer dyde offende</l>
               <l>Whiche by an euyll tonge is brought to dyſſhonoure</l>
               <l>And in to an euyll name ſone they be comptende</l>
               <l>That a. M. to theyr good name cannot them reſtore</l>
               <l>The claterers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycyon is to groſe vp more &amp; more</l>
               <l>Maydens by them is blamed wedowes &amp; other mo</l>
               <l>For by an euyll tonge the name is ſoone go</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There is many one blamed and accuſed for nought</l>
               <l>And many gyltles theyr lyues fro them is take</l>
               <l>Ye and a thouſande into pouerte brought</l>
               <l>That dayly goth a begy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; prayed for goddes ſake</l>
               <l>And all thorowe tale tellers his ſcrowe doth wake</l>
               <l>Whiche cauſed many one theyr ſelfe to ſlo</l>
               <l>Where by an euyll tonge theyr good name is a go</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Full many be brought to dyſeas and captyuyte</l>
               <l>In euery regyon that man can trauayll</l>
               <l>The tonge is cauſer of this wofull aduerſyte</l>
               <l>Full lytell or nought now dooth trouth auayll</l>
               <l>True heyers be dyſheryte without ony fayll</l>
               <l>With wepynge &amp; waylynge ſome waxeth blynde</l>
               <l>And all cauſeth euyll to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges mooſt enemy to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoughe ſome preeſtes now be neuer ſo pacyent</l>
               <l>And in towne and cyte be peaſe ouer all</l>
               <l>Or though the relygyous be neuer ſo obedyent</l>
               <l>Yet an euyll tonge wyll trouble them all</l>
               <l>Multyplyenge of leſynges by hym aryſe ſhall</l>
               <l>To trouble good people in ſoule and mynde</l>
               <l>This is euyll tonges mooſt enemy to mankynde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11124:3"/>
               <l>Yf ony man wolde begynne his ſynnes to reny</l>
               <l>Or ony good people that fro vyce dyde refrayne</l>
               <l>What ſo euer he were that to vertue wolde applye</l>
               <l>But an yll tonge wyll all ouerthrowe agayne</l>
               <l>Lo by whome is rayſed all this grete payne</l>
               <l>Of ſorowefull ſclaunder that flyeth as the wynde</l>
               <l>Theſe yll tonges be mooſt enemy to mankynde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſaye not but warre is grete abuſyon</l>
               <l>Yet is there not ſo many as is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yll tonges ſlayne</l>
               <l>And though honger be neuer ſo ſharpe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeaſon</l>
               <l>Yet for all that god ſome people doth ſuſtayne</l>
               <l>Of froſtes grete ſome people be not fayne</l>
               <l>But ſo ſore grefe no where may we fynde</l>
               <l>As it the yll tonge mooſt enemy to mankynge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though ſodayne deth be neuer ſo rygorous</l>
               <l>Yet by preeſtes it ſeaſeth at the laſte</l>
               <l>But where all yll tonges lyſte to be malycyous</l>
               <l>There is neuer remedy whan the worde is paſt</l>
               <l>To lye and ſaye wronge they be neuer agaſt</l>
               <l>Of heuen and hell they haue lytell mynde</l>
               <l>I meane yll tonges mooſt enemy to man kynde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Speke of ſalpeter arſnek or ony poyſon mortall</l>
               <l>The fyre of hell the blood of ſerpentes venymmous</l>
               <l>Ye fynde none ſone ſo peryllous amonge all</l>
               <l>As is the yll tonge to them that be vertuous</l>
               <l>They be of malyce ſo full and rygorous</l>
               <l>For they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyſte to do well &amp; ther o do theyr payne</l>
               <l>By the euyll tongue all is ouerthrowe agayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11124:4"/>
               <l>Therfore euery creature take hede what ye ſaye</l>
               <l>For yf the worde be eſcaped at any throwe</l>
               <l>It wyll not be called agayne though y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wolde laye</l>
               <l>Bothe lyfe and goodes and on it beſtowe</l>
               <l>I wolde wete how we a good tongue ſholde knowe</l>
               <l>It wyll not be for by the ſubtyll trayne</l>
               <l>Of the yll tongue whiche all ouerthroweth agayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Men ſhette ſurely theyr chyſtes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyluer &amp; golde</l>
               <l>With dyuyrs Iulles of grete comodytes</l>
               <l>Furred gownes in grayne ryght goodly to beholde</l>
               <l>Yet were they better to kepe theyr aduerſaryes cloſe</l>
               <l>The yll tonge and ſette all the other loſe</l>
               <l>For many hath purpoſed to amende w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> herte fayne</l>
               <l>But an yll tonge ouerthroweth agayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For that yll by another dothe ſaye</l>
               <l>Yf he his owne defautes dyde well beholde</l>
               <l>How many tymes hymſelfe is out of the waye</l>
               <l>Full gladly than his tonge kepe he wolde</l>
               <l>For yf pykethankes theyr owne fautes ſe ſholde</l>
               <l>To theyr hertes it wolde be a grete payne</l>
               <l>For by yll tonges all vertue is ouerthrowe agayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All people beware of theſe yll tonges moſt peryllous</l>
               <l>And eſchewe them where euer you go</l>
               <l>Tonge breketh bone he is ſo malycyous</l>
               <l>And none hath hymſelfe all knoweth it is ſo</l>
               <l>Sclander cometh lyghtly whiche cauſeth grete wo</l>
               <l>For though thou be in name I tell the playne</l>
               <l>By an yll tonge all is ouerthrowen agayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11124:4"/>
               <l>Theſe comberoſe clamores in euery towne</l>
               <l>That thynge whiche the deuyll can not bry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge about</l>
               <l>An yll tonge wyll performe by vnkynde perolyſene</l>
               <l>Yf a thouſande fendes were to gyder in a route</l>
               <l>Coude not by theyr malyce ſuche falſhede vter oute</l>
               <l>To brynge the people to grete deſſenſyon</l>
               <l>As doth theſe yll tonges mannes mooſt confuſyon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O enuyous tonges deſtroyers of hye &amp; lowe degre</l>
               <l>Thy wycked ſedes thou doeſt ſowe downe</l>
               <l>Here and elles where ouer euery countre</l>
               <l>Bothe in cyte borowe vyllage and towne</l>
               <l>Seaſe thy rorynge thou fendly lyon</l>
               <l>In the coffer of ſcyence hyde the full ſoone</l>
               <l>For yll tonges is mannes moſt confuſyon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that can kepe his tonge and beware</l>
               <l>Laude vnto hym ſhall euer encreaſe</l>
               <l>And where that euer he go he nede not to care</l>
               <l>For he is ſure of reſte and peaſe</l>
               <l>More of this mater I nede not reherſe</l>
               <l>For take theſe wordes for a concluſyon</l>
               <l>That yll tonges is euer mannes confuſyon</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>¶Amen.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:11124:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of William Caxton with the sun and stars in the top register, appropriated by Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
                  <p>W <gap reason="symbol" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> C</p>
                  <p>wynkyn · de · worde.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11124:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
